<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | Dr. Halley Pontes</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/publications/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:4321/media/icon_hu3916292783086637300.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/publications/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the interplay between gaming disorder and functional impairments in professional esports gaming</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between Gaming Disorder (GD) and the experience of functional impairments
has received considerable theoretical attention in the recent past and current diagnostic
approaches underscore the centrality of functional impairments as a requirement for GD diagnosis.
However, there is limited empirical evidence illuminating the interplay between GD and functional
impairments, particularly among specific vulnerable groups. The present study seeks to bridge this
gap by investigating an English-speaking sample (&lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 5198) comprising an age- and gender-matched
group of Professional Gamers (PG, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 2599) and Non-Professional Gamers (NPG, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 2599) sub-sampled
from a larger sample of 192,260 individuals. The results revealed that PG were at a greater risk
for GD compared to NPG as the prevalence rate of GD among PG (3.31%) was significantly higher and
almost doubled that of NPG (1.73%), with PG further exhibiting higher overall GD symptom-load and
weekly time spent gaming compared to NPG. Furthermore, PG reported experiencing significantly higher
frequency of gaming-related functional impairments compared to NPG, with the in particular affected
areas for both PG and NPG being &lt;em&gt;‘school and/or work’&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;‘physical health’&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;‘family’&lt;/em&gt;, with other key
differences emerging in relation to other outcomes. Overall, the present findings show that not only
GD symptom-load but also some functional impairment is higher in PG compared to NPG which highlights
the need to develop and support prevention and intervention strategies for this at-risk population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral Addictions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/books/book-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/books/book-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book provides a holistic evidence-based perspective on conceptual, clinical, assessment, and
treatment aspects of key non-substance-based addictive disorders related to: gambling, gaming, social media,
smartphone, internet, love, sex, exercise, work, and shopping. Each chapter focuses on a different addictive
disorder and is structured in a user-friendly way to enable the reader fast navigation, yet the main aspects
of the respective disorders are covered in the necessary depth. All in all, this book offers a timely,
self-contained introduction to both key concepts and the latest scientific developments in behavioral addictions.
It addresses mental health practitioners, researchers in psychology, neuroscience and communication, and undergraduate
and postgraduate students alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gambling Disorder (Mark D. Griffiths, Filipa Calado)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gaming Disorder (Cuneyt Evren)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Media Addiction (Tayana Panova, Xavier Carbonell)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smartphone Addiction (Dmitri Rozgonjuk, Christian Montag, Jon D. Elhai)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet Addiction (Halley M. Pontes, Jason Satel, Almuth McDowall)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love Addiction (Taya Bockmann, Marsal Sanches)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sex Addiction (Manpreet Dhuffar-Pottiwal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise Addiction (Attila Szabo, Krisztina Ábel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work Addiction (Paweł Andrzej Atroszko)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shopping Addiction (Aniko Maraz, Sebastiano Costa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a copy now from&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-031-04772-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Springer Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Behavioral-Addictions-Conceptual-Assessment-Approaches/dp/3031047737&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Behavioral-Addictions-Conceptual-Assessment-Neuroscience/dp/3031047710&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The interplay between time spent gaming and disordered gaming: A large-scale world-wide study</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: ‘Gaming Disorder’ (GD) is now an officially recognized mental health disorder according
to the World Health Organization (WHO) framework while ‘Internet Gaming Disorder (IGD) remains as
a tentative disorder as per the American Psychiatric Association (APA) framework. Although both GD
and IGD reflect disordered gaming tendencies marked by excessive time spent gaming, little is known
about the extent to which too much time spent gaming becomes particularly problematic. Moreover, emerging
research has highlighted the need to further explore how both disordered gaming frameworks perform in
the assessment and estimation of disordered gaming symptoms and related behaviors. Methods: The primary
aim of the present study was to shed light on the complex relationship between time spent gaming and
disordered gaming and to provide prevalence estimates of disordered gaming across the WHO and APA frameworks.
This study adopted an online survey methodology and a cross-sectional design in a large sample of 123,262
eligible gamers from 168 countries. Results: The results obtained indicated that the prevalence rate
of disordered gaming among the participants was smaller when assessed with the WHO framework (i.e., 1.96%)
in comparison to the APA framework (i.e., 4.97%). Additionally, the relationship between time spent gaming
and disordered gaming varied, and disordered gaming was associated on average with 34.53 h of gaming a
week within the APA framework (i.e., with at least five criteria endorsed; higher gaming-time-averages
for those endorsing more criteria) and an average of 40.13 h a week within the WHO framework (i.e., with all
criteria endorsed). Conclusions: The relationship between weekly time spent gaming and disordered gaming is
multifaceted and varies according to the diagnostic framework adopted. The results highlight the need for
further refinement at the diagnostic level in regard to disordered gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measurement and Conceptualization of Gaming Disorder According to the World Health Organization Framework:the Development of the Gaming Disorder Test</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous research on gaming disorder (GD) has highlighted key methodological and conceptual
hindrances stemming from the heterogeneity of nomenclature and the use of non-standardized
psychometric tools to assess this phenomenon. The recent recognition of GD as an official mental
health disorder and behavioral addiction by the World Health Organization (WHO) in the 11th
Revision of the International Classification of Diseases (ICD-11) opens up new possibilities to
investigate further the psychosocial and mental health implications due to excessive and disordered
gaming. However, before further research on GD can be conducted in a reliable way and within a robust
cross-cultural context, a valid and reliable standardized psychometric tool to assess the construct as
defined by the WHO should be developed. The aim of this study was to develop The Gaming Disorder
Test (GDT), a brief four-item measure to assess GD and to further explore its psychometric properties.
A sample of 236 Chinese (47% male, mean age 19.22 years, SD = 1.57) and 324 British (49.4% male, mean
age 26.74 years, SD = 7.88) gamers was recruited online. Construct validity of the GDT was examined
via factorial validity, nomological validity, alongside convergent and discriminant validity. Concurrent
validity was also examined using the Internet Gaming Disorder Scale—Short-Form (IGDS9-SF). Finally, reliability
indicators involving the Cronbach’s alpha and composite reliability coefficients were estimated. Overall,
the results indicated that GDT is best conceptualized within a single-factor structure. Additionally, the
four items of the GDT are valid, reliable, and proved to be highly suitable for measuring GD within a
cross-cultural context.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critically appraising the pitfalls of screen time effects research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2020-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2020-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existing recommendations regulating screen time use and studies investigating its effects are
inherently problematic for two main reasons. First, they imply that screen time activities are essentially
the same in nature regardless of what type of digital content is being consumed. This phenomenon has been
described as monolithic screen time, which refers to an assessment approach to screen time implying that all
screen time activities are qualitatively and psychologically equivalent. This assessment may be one of the main
reasons leading researchers to report conflicting evidence in relation to the potential role of screen time in
enhancing and/ or deteriorating psychological health and well-being of users. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/0004867420963736&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[continued&amp;hellip;]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new era for gaming disorder research: Time to shift from consensus to consistency</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2020-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2020-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The release of the first commercial video games occurred in the early 1970s and it took approximately 10 years
for the first reports of what we would now term ‘Gaming Disorder’ (GD) to emerge in the scientific literature
(Ross, Finestone, &amp;amp; Lavin, 1982). More recently, research on GD has received much public and scientific scrutiny
due to the increasing importance given to this condition by official medical and psychiatric organizations
(Pontes &amp;amp; Griffiths, 2014). This led to three key milestones in the field. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106059&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;[continued&amp;hellip;]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internet Addiction</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/books/book-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/books/book-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book examines how you can identify, assess, and treat Internet addiction in the most effective manner.
Internet use has become an integral part of our daily lives, but at what point does Internet use become problematic?
What are the different kinds of Internet addiction? And how can professionals best help clients? Internet addiction
refers to a range of behavioral problems, including social media addiction and Internet gaming disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This compact, evidence-based guide written by leading experts from the field helps disentangle the debates
and controversies around Internet addiction and outlines the current assessment and treatment methods.
The book presents a 12–15 session treatment plan for Internet and gaming addiction using the method and setting
with the best evidence: group CBT. Printable tools in the appendix help clinicians implement therapy.
This accessible book is essential reading for clinical psychologists, psychiatrists, psychotherapists,
counsellors, social workers, teachers, as well as students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a copy now from&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hogrefe.com/uk/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hogrefe UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hogrefe.com/eu/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hogrefe EU Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hogrefe.com/us/shop/internet-addiction-76323.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hogrefe US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Internet-Addiction-2018-Advances-Psychotherapy/dp/0889375011&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon UK Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Internet-Addiction-Advances-Psychotherapy-Evidence-Based/dp/0889375011&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon US Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From the reviewers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek Boan, MD, Psychotherapist, writing in Medical Psychotherapy Review, 26 (2), 9-10 (2019):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, on a topical issue, needed to be written! A well-researched, well-organized, concise book about
a complex issue that plagues societies around the world. Internet Addiction is divided into four sections:
Description, Theories and Model of Internet Addiction, Diagnosis and Treatment Indications, and Treatment.
[It] provides an overview to a blossoming worldwide problem … a foundation upon which to build, in terms of definition,
verified assessment tools, comorbidities, and treatment plans. As a bonus, after reading this book, psychologists and
other healthcare providers can earn continuing education credits by completing a multiple-choice exam through the
National Register of Health Service Psychologists, as approved by the American Psychological Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hilarie Cash, PhD, Chief Clinical Officer and Co-Founder of reSTART Life, PLLC, Fall City, WA –
the first residential treatment program for Internet addiction in the US:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This excellent book is a pleasure to read. It provides up-to-date coverage of the research
findings on Internet addiction, clarifies the areas needing further research, and offers valuable,
practical information on the best-studied treatment approaches. At a time when clinicians are scrambling
to learn what they can about the rapidly developing problem of Internet addiction, this book offers them
an excellent place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Richard Graham, Consultant Child &amp;amp; Adolescent Psychiatrist, Technology Addiction Service,
Nightingale Hospital, London, UK; Clinical Director, Good Thinking – The London Digital Mental
Well-Being Service; Executive Board, UK Council for Child Internet Safety (UKCCIS):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the researcher, clinician, or anyone who has concerns about how the Internet is shaping our lives,
this is an essential collection of the latest research evidence and thinking on Internet addiction.
The refreshing lack of bias in consideration of our knowledge to date of this complex and controversial
problem does not shy away from the reality that for some, their Internet activities are beyond their control.
Exploring causation, assessment, therapeutic approaches, and prognosis, there is much to guide and inform
both the health practitioner and academic researcher in our unprecedented times. Excellent!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Henrietta Bowden-Jones, FRCPsych, BA(Hons), DOccMed, MD(Imperial),
Royal College of Psychiatrists Spokesperson on Behavioural Addictions, London, UK:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuss and Pontes’ Internet Addiction provides not only a much-needed history of the evolution of
Internet disorders and their global prevalence, but also teaches clinicians how to tackle their treatment.
This is a book to include on the reading list for any mental health professionals wanting to know more about
one of the ‘new’ addictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zsolt Demetrovics, PhD, Professor of Psychology at ELTE Eötvös Loránd University,
Budapest, Hungary; Editor-in-Chief, Journal of Behavioral Addictions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excellent overview of Internet addiction, one of today’s most exciting and pressing mental
health issues. The emergence of the Internet and the accompanying developments in information and communication
technology have impacted substantially on our everyday lives, bringing both new possibilities and new problems.
This book provides a comprehensive overview of research done on Internet addiction and related disorders over the
past two decades and, crucially, introduces therapeutic interventions that have been shown to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the differential effects of social networking site addiction and Internet gaming disorder on psychological health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background and aims: Previous studies focused on examining the interrelationships between social
networking site (SNS) addiction and Internet gaming disorder (IGD) in isolation. Moreover, little
is known about the potential simultaneous differential effects of SNS addiction and IGD on psychological
health. This study investigated the interplay between these two technological addictions and ascertained
how they can uniquely and distinctively contribute to increasing psychiatric distress when accounting for
potential effects stemming from sociodemographic and technology-related variables. Methods: A sample of
509 adolescents (53.5% males) aged 10–18 years (mean = 13.02, SD = 1.64) were recruited. Results: It was
found that key demographic variables can play a distinct role in explaining SNS addiction and IGD. Furthermore,
it was found that SNS addiction and IGD can augment the symptoms of each other, and simultaneously contribute
to deterioration of overall psychological health in a similar fashion, further highlighting potentially common
etiological and clinical course between these two phenomena. Finally, the detrimental effects of IGD on psychological
health were found to be slightly more pronounced than those produced by SNS addiction, a finding that warrants
additional scientific scrutiny. Discussion and conclusion: The implications of these results are further discussed
in light of the existing evidence and debates regarding the status of technological addictions as primary and
secondary disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Conceptualisation and Measurement of DSM-5 Internet Gaming Disorder: The Development of the IGD-20 Test</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/publication/2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/publication/2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: Over the last decade, there has been growing concern about ‘gaming addiction’ and
its widely documented detrimental impacts on a minority of individuals that play excessively. The latest
(fifth) edition of the American Psychiatric Association&amp;rsquo;s Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental
Disorders (DSM-5) included nine criteria for the potential diagnosis of Internet Gaming Disorder (IGD)
and noted that it was a condition that warranted further empirical study. Aim: The main aim of this study
was to develop a valid and reliable standardised psychometrically robust tool in addition to providing
empirically supported cut-off points. Methods: A sample of 1003 gamers (85.2% males; mean age 26 years)
from 57 different countries were recruited via online gaming forums. Validity was assessed by confirmatory
factor analysis (CFA), criterion-related validity, and concurrent validity. Latent profile analysis was also
carried to distinguish disordered gamers from non-disordered gamers. Sensitivity and specificity analyses were
performed to determine an empirical cut-off for the test. Results: The CFA confirmed the viability of
IGD-20 Test with a six-factor structure (salience, mood modification, tolerance, withdrawal, conflict
and relapse) for the assessment of IGD according to the nine criteria from DSM-5. The IGD-20 Test proved
to be valid and reliable. According to the latent profile analysis, 5.3% of the total participants were
classed as disordered gamers. Additionally, an optimal empirical cut-off of 71 points (out of 100) seemed
to be adequate according to the sensitivity and specificity analyses carried. Conclusions: The present
findings support the viability of the IGD-20 Test as an adequate standardised psychometrically robust tool
for assessing internet gaming disorder. Consequently, the new instrument represents the first step towards
unification and consensus in the field of gaming studies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
